Idaho has a lot of terrain
from tall, snowy mountains
to flat, dry deserts.
Before you leave town
to go hit the great outdoors,
make sure you ask yourself:
Am I ready for this hike?
Hiking can mean a lot of different
things depending on who you ask.
It could be something simple, like walking
through the woods after dinner,
or summiting some of
the tallest peaks in the state.
Make sure no matter where
you're heading outdoors,
you go prepared for any scenario.
The “Ten Essentials” is a list of
basic survival items
that's been around for decades.
And no, it's not a bunch of expensive
gear you have to go buy.
It's ten categories of things
that you should pack to help
keep you safe in the backcountry.
First things first,
you need to know where you're going.
That can be with a paper map and a compass,
or with a GPS, or
even directions from your phone.
But don't rely on an internet connection
once you get out there.
Next, you're going to want
to dress in layers
so that you can adapt
to the changing trail conditions.
Sure, that extra shirt is going to be nice
in the morning when it's shady,
but in the afternoon in the sun
you might be a little uncomfortable.
Speaking of that afternoon sun,
you also need something
to protect yourself from it.
That could be sunglasses, sunscreen,
a wide brimmed hat,
something to keep you from getting burned.
And yes, you need to remember it
even when it's cold out
because that white winter snow
still reflects the sun.
On the other hand,
if things start to get dark,
you should have a light source with you.
A headlamp is a great hands free option
as long as you remember
to make sure it has fresh batteries.
Not only should you bring water
along in a bottle or a reservoir,
some experts say you should bring
an entire day's extra with you.
And food might seem like a no brainer,
but make sure it's something
that will sustain your energy
throughout the day.
The last essentials to pack
include a pocket knife or multi-tool,
a way to start and maintain a fire,
an emergency shelter and a first aid kit.
These categories are just recommendations
and the items in them can be tailored
depending on how intense your hike is.
And just like with any gear.
It's not going to help you
if you don't know how to use it.
So make sure you're familiar
with the kit that you pack.
So next time you're
headed for the great outdoors,
make sure you pack everything
for a fun, safe hike.
If you liked this video,
let us know by clicking the like button.
Check out the description for links
to our printable “Ten Essentials” checklist
and trail recommendations
courtesy of Visit Idaho
and leave us a comment
about your favorite places to hike.
Subscribe to the channel
for more local content like this
and we'll see you on the trail.