You know, US history is that
we started by seceding from Great Britain,
right?
I mean, we said we're not
we don't want to be a part of that.
So our American Revolution begins.
You know, this story of us saying, no,
we don't want that.
We want something else.
And so that,
that sort of begat all of these other
kinds of movements,
including the US Civil War, that ends up,
you know, these breaking away
and sort of forming new things,
sort of baked into the DNA for Americans.
In a way.
One of the people who seemed to be
a larger than life figure, particularly
after the Civil War, is Senator
Orville Platt from from Connecticut.
So, I mean,
you had this he was one of these four
Republican senators who basically set
the agenda for much of the legislation
of the late 19th century.
And he,
he had definite opinions
about, state development
and things that he wanted to see,
you know, as criteria
for what constituted a good state.
Things like, you know,
that they needed to be,
you know, of a right size.
So, you know, trying to figure out
what's the right mixture of a state
that had enough population
but also had enough territory.
But,
it could be also sort of self-sufficient
and then also, like,
you know, that they were willing to adopt,
a, a smaller Republican government,
you know, with the Constitution
and representatives
and that sort of stuff.
So it it was a sort of mixture
that he was looking
for, in, you know,
the development of these states.
So he was one of the big,
factors in
like breaking up Dakota Territory
into north and south because he thought
if they admitted it as just one big state,
that that was too large for people
to be able to interact with,
their state government would be too far
and costly for people to travel, to
go to the state legislature, to, you know,
the 1787 Northwest Ordinance, you know,
which predates the US Constitution.
But that's the thing that sort of sets up
this,
system
for how we turn a territory into a state.
And sort of so that that's part of it.
So there's sort of this colonial,
leftover
some of the ideas from the British,
that are part of that.
Then you get a Jefferson who is interested
in, the yeoman farmer agrarian,
sort of vision of the United States.
And it was very,
enamored with squares or rectangles.
And then you've got Lincoln as well,
who's sort of in this mix, who's, adding
some different elements when it comes to,
his interest in the West.
So, you know, I mean,
starting in the middle of the Civil War,
he's thinking about the Homestead Act.
He's thinking about
the transcontinental railroad, and he's
thinking about land grant colleges.
You know, in the
midst of utter chaos,
that is the Civil war.
But add in there to the fact
that he is also faced with West Virginia.
So breaking off part of Virginia
that did not want to go with,
the Confederacy.
So you've got, you know,
a variety of different issues happening
that sort of have their roots
in the Lincoln administration, which,
I think is also part of the interest in,
naming
possibly a state after Lincoln.
There was, some,
some sort of, interest in naming
North Dakota Lincoln,
the state of Lincoln.
And,
it was rejected as a possible state name,
but that was sort of set out in,
in the 1787 Northwest Orient Ordinance.
So that's the that ordinance set up the,
the process for how we deal with,
you know, new territory.
And that became sort of the guide for us.
And it's an interesting thing
because it was set up
during the Articles of Confederation,
which was pre United States of America.
And it's but
it was such an important issue
that the United States needed to settle.
What do we do with this new Ohio
territory,
that we have,
how are we going to manage this?
And they couldn't
wait until a constitution was drafted.
So they're almost like parallel processes,
the Articles of Confederation,
Northwest Ordinance
and the US Constitution, which is being,
you know, worked on in seventh
that summer of 1787.
And Philadelphia, they're happening
almost at the same time.
So it sort of gives you a sense
that, oh, like, wow, this land issue
and how these states are going to be
developed, is, is important.
It's, you know, it has even longer roots
than, than the Constitution. So,
so that act continues to inform,
you know, how the process
for these things
and setting things up
on a rectangular grid system
and that so that all of that
is part of the Northwest Ordinance.
And of course, it gets,
codified in the US Constitution.
Article four, section
three sort of says that, you know,
the process for creating new states
and, you know, that that,
that these things are set out
and the process resides with Congress,
which is sort of an interesting part
of this thing.
That is, I think most people forget
because we haven't
created a new state in a long time.
Is that Congress
is the one driving this process?
And so the Constitution says
it's Congress
and these state legislatures
that are the ones that are,
that are going to have to
figure this out, of course.
Territory territories, which
is sort of the first part of this process,
are directly under the federal government.
So they have very few
rights.
They're not states yet.
So there's not all of this
federal state kinds of division.
So territories are like this
weird in-between state,
and they don't have any senators.
They don't have any, representatives
in the House.
They have territorial delegates
who can have,
they can give speeches.
They could,
you know, lobby other members of Congress,
but they have no voting rights.
You know,
wherever Americans have moved out,
you know,
as they sort of making their way west,
they bring themselves with them
and they also bring with them sort
of these regional,
differences, regional sensibilities.
So you do get folks from the South
who are moving to Oregon
and to Idaho, to Washington state,
and as they're moving west, you know,
through the Oregon Trail and those things,
they,
want to keep abreast of these issues.
So it's always surprising to me.
I think it's probably less so now, in my
career, but it continues to, to sort of,
bring home the fact that, you know,
the stories that they're reading in
newspapers are stories from back East,
and they're very interested in Bleeding
Kansas.
You know, these fights
that are happening in the 1850s.
They are interested in John Brown's
raid and Harpers Ferry.
They're following the news very closely
as best they can, given, you know, the
distance and time it took for newspapers
to make it west in these stories.
But they are
they are tuned in and they both men,
Lincoln and Douglas,
are from the state of Illinois.
But both of them were keenly interested
in affairs in the West.
They were both really closely
watching things out
West and were very interested
in, in what was happening in the US West.
So, so they were
they were really probably plugged in more
than some of their other contemporaries
who could have cared less
about what was happening.
The pre-Civil War era was kind of this,
this balancing
act of free state slave state.
So trying to figure out, to keep
the balance in the Senate in particular.
And then after the Civil War,
it isn't so much of this,
you know, sort
of one state and another state
sort of in pairs.
There was more of the sense of,
can we get a block of them together?
Can we sort of do a bill
that would would allow
a bunch of these states
sort of to come in at the same time?
There are political considerations.
And that's the thing
I think that did not change.
So, you know, there was this
calculus of slave versus free,
pre-Civil War politics never goes away
in the creation of states.
And so there is this sense of,
is this going to be a Republican
leaning state and a Democrat,
the sort of state like so which,
which, you know, are we going to try
to keep keep this balance going?
And so there are
those considerations happening,
and all of this as well,
so that that factors into it.
Plus,
you know, race plays a role in this.
So some places like, the
what would was termed
the Indian Territory,
in Oklahoma, like, do we admit Oklahoma
and an Indian territory like,
so the eastern part of Oklahoma,
which was considered Indian Territory
in the western Panhandle
as something different?
So there were debates about that.
But there was sort of slowing
down of these places like New Mexico
and even Arizona,
because there were so many,
indigenous,
folks who were,
you know, the border
sort of crossed them in the US-Mexico war.
So there were some
racial considerations as well about,
you know,
do we really want to include, you know,
those people, as,
you know, as full citizens
in the United States?
Again, Franklin was actually called
Franklin County, Deseret Territory,
and they would actually send
in their taxes into Utah.
The first settlers that came here
and actually filed their property
on their, through Utah,
through Deseret Territory,
and that's where they,
had legally owned their property
beginning before Idaho was created.
And then once Idaho was created,
they had to refile on the land
they were already living on in
Idaho Territory.
They had, disputed the boundary line
because no official survey had been done.
So the residents of Frankland,
had disputed it.
And in 1872, when the survey part
party came through,
they definitely said yes.
Franklin was an Idaho Territory
because residents
had believed that
after the creation of Idaho Territory,
the boundary line was actually further up
closer to Downey area.
And with that first official survey party
coming through,
then they know
they definitely were in Idaho Territory.
And so needless to say, they could claim
that they had both been in Utah and Idaho.
And it gave, Franklin the distinction
of being the first permanent settlement
in the state of Idaho than the,
as we have a long history here
of historical buildings
and Franklin being the first permanent
settlement in Franklin and Idaho.
And so Franklin is blessed
with a lot of old buildings,
graciously, throughout time,
the Idaho State Historical Society
has taken over those buildings,
caring for them and maintaining them.
And in turn, we've got the Franklin rally
called Museum and which we're and right
now, also, we have the Carmichael
building here next to us.
And it was built in 1868.
It was made from quarried rock,
and it was ripped to be the first store
in the state of Idaho.
Franklin tends to have a lot of first,
because of its early,
permanent settlement distinction.
And then next to that
we have the Lorenzo Hill Hatch Hall
and then a John Pony cabin.
And so the Historical Society,
under the direction of the Idaho
State, manages and operates
the site for visitors to come visit
and learn more about the early history
in southeast Idaho down here.
So the Lorenzo Hatch home,
was acquired by the historical Society
and 2010 time period descendants
from Lorenzo Hill
hatch had actually live next to the home,
and he had had a carpenter shop
in his home.
When he passed away,
the home came up for sale,
and the Idaho State Historical Society
purchased that, and now it has been
refitted and
and changed to be an interpretive center.
Even though was kept the classic rock
look on the outside and inside
there are interpretive panels of the state
of Idaho's early beginnings down here.
Representing Lake Bonneville,
the early native Indians,
and the time period
from the settlement of Franklin
up now, the rental hill
hatch was pretty important.
A gentleman in history.
He was, also one of the first legislators
that went to Boise.
He, when Franklin became part of Idaho
in 1873, he went up
and, was in the legislator legislation
there and brought the charter for Franklin
to become a city or a village.
At the time.
And so he was able to get that charter
and bring that back.
There was a few other bills
he submitted, but they were not passed
during that session.
But he was comfortable going there
because he had already been
in the Utah legislature,
because he came from Levi,
Utah in 1863 and moved up here
to build up the community.
And he had already served two different
terms down in Utah and Deseret Territory.
So he was used to being in government.
Yes. So in 1859, they came and settled,
into Cache Valley and
I actually
was born and raised in Wellsville,
Utah, in the southern part of the valley.
And they came to settle.
Wellsville first, and then, started
progressing further up
into the northern part of Cache Valley.
Now, the pioneers that came to settle here
actually wanted to grow up
around sort of springs and settle.
But, their leader,
who most of them joined the LDS church,
which was Brigham Young at the time,
he he contacted them to be able to now
go no farther
than the northern end of Cache Valley.
And so they came here and settled and,
after they were here for a while,
then they started going to Bear Lake area
and settling there,
obviously in Franklin County, they went
and settled the other communities
of Dayton, Weston,
Clifton, Oxford,
and then up to Preston,
which is our county seat now, here
and then further up into down in the area
and even after the Homestead
Act opened up,
and you were able to go further into Idaho
and pick up a lot more property,
then a lot of them moved up to Idaho
Falls, Rexburg
and Ashland,
and throughout the state of Idaho.
Franklin sits
really in a good position
because obviously you had
the Oregon Trail, the Californian trail,
and the Mormon Trail.
That's how we came west.
You know, if you went down on the through
southern Utah,
but most of them came west in that area.
So north of us sits the Oregon Trail
and splits
off the California Trail
and then the Mormon Trail.
And so Franklin has a good
handle on the different immigrants
that were coming through and heading,
obviously, to California for the gold rush
and then up
into further into Idaho and Washington
and typically
people would move to an area
because of opportunity.
And that's the same reason
that people came to Franklin and then
moved on to other parts in the West
is because there was opportunity.
And so what they brought with them
was, was the American spirit.
A lot of them were immigrants
into America.
Some of them had ancestors
that were along the East Coast
that farther from their freedom
in the Revolutionary War,
some of them just, you know,
all that decided they wanted to come west.
And so they were coming for opportunity.
And what they brought with them
was a lot of hard work and dedication.
And they all want one thing
to have a happy home for their
families and their children.
And so,
yes, I
would say that Franklin does represent
the American spirit of building
beautiful communities,
have prospering, having businesses
and growing and sharing
what they have and their area with others.
Before the railroad,
the transcontinental railroad,
it took quite a while
to come across the plains,
and so they wanted to connect both sides
of the country and from east to west.
And so the transcontinental railroad
was going to be an amazing,
amazing thing that would benefit
the people that were already in the West.
And, Lorenzo Hatch,
he, with a group of gentlemen
here from Franklin, actually went out
and had contracts with the Central Pacific
just west of promontory to lay the,
the last part of the railroad grade
to promontory.
And they, worked on that railroad.
But the other half of the gentleman
here in Franklin
had to work on this Acme Co-op building.
So there was a store for those people
that were coming on
the transcontinental railroad to shop at
in the communities once they did get here.
So the railroad would benefit
the communities as bringing additional,
settlers and immigrants
in and business and opportunity
and Ashley Franklin, after they had
the transcontinental railroad built,
became the end of the line for the Utah
Northern that branched off from there.
And so it sat in Franklin
for quite a while,
and there was a number of freighters
that would go and head up to the Montana
goldfields, hauling
freight from Franklin and there.
Eventually the railroad
pressed further into Idaho,
and it was able to have a huge impact
in the state of Idaho.
And so the railroad
was a big benefit to the state.
So Eliot Butterworth was a man of vision.
He there's no other words to call him
because
he actually came to America.
In 1868 on the first passenger car
on the transcontinental railroad
to the west.
And his family had just got here right
as they had finished the
transcontinental railroad.
So him and his mother and a sister
were there, and an uncle in their family
came to the West,
and he worked for the railroad.
He was a the perfect age,
to work and helped
build the railroad here to Franklin.
And then he went to southern
Utah and worked on the railroad there,
and then came back
and he could see
through the next 20 or 30 years
that all the original,
settlers that had came and settled
the area were starting to pass away.
And he wanted to retain
their important stories
because a lot of them had,
played a big impact in American history.
Through, like I said, on
along the East Coast, through the South,
coming across the plains,
they they all had a huge impact.
So he wanted to retain their stories,
not just what they ended their lives
with here in Franklin,
but other contributions
that they had given
and other parts of the surrounding state.
And so he started collecting artifacts
of those individuals in the early 1900s.
And he had a store and he,
would pick up a, artifact.
Here they are.
As they were passing away,
he would go to their children and ask them
if they would donate an artifact of theirs
so their memory could be remembered.
In 1910, when a group of Franklin,
settlers had gone to the governor
and petitioned
that Franklin be officially, recognized
as the first permanent settlement.
Then he granted that request
after affidavits
had been submitted to him,
and they were given the honor
of being the first permanent settlement.
And Franklin
and they put together a small
committee of individuals
that want to preserve the history of that.
And in 1910
they created the official, June
15th of Idaho Days
for an annual celebration of that event.
And to honor these individuals each year.
And so Elliot continued
to collect these items
belonging to the pioneers,
and he put them in his store.
And when he realized
the store was getting way too small
to hold all the artifacts he had
collected, then, during the depression,
when the New Deal came forward,
then he thought he'd get
some of that money to help
build a museum for those artifacts.
So he once again,
worked with the Franklin County office,
and then they went to the state
and asked for a grant to build
the Franklin
Relic Hall Museum tax artifact collection.
And this building was built to
and from the WPA program.
And the keys
to be able to house the collection
that he had been,
collecting through the years.
And so this building
and is dedicated really to his memory
because he oversaw the building,
the timbers were cut and the canyon up
by the CCS and then brought down
and built here for his collection.
So he did not just want to tell the story
of individuals here in the community,
but he would travel throughout
the United States picking up rare
and unique artifacts
to be able to be in this, museum.
He had, gone
to actually made a trip to England
because that's where he was from.
And on his way there,
he was stopping at every museum
to see how they had laid out their
collections and how they displayed them,
and what was unique in those museums
that he was visiting because he wanted
to bring that back here to Franklin
and have it in this museum.
And at one point, the newspapers did claim
that this was one of the biggest museums
in the West.
And so he had gained, what his desire
was to make it, an amazing museum.
And we have artifacts
that a lot of museums you would not
believe were in here just because,
like I said, he was a man of vision
and he could see the important items
and was collecting them.
And during that time period, the
those events were happening in history.
Leah would like to go to the enjoyed going
and traveling to the world fairs.
And so he was a man
that like new inventions, his
he even brought over
some top hats from England
that his father and his uncle
had wore at the first demonstration of the
train engines
that were
operating in England at the time.
So before he immigrated, they went
and they saw that new invention
and how that would change life,
with the steam engine.
And so he was he enjoyed, science
and learning about different things
that were happening.
So he would like to
he went to the world's fairs
and he would bring back artifacts
from the World's Fair.
He went to the Panama Expo,
and we have some artifacts from that expo
that he had brought back with,
he also liked to see,
you know, whether in fact.
So he would he went to the San Francisco
earthquake and brought back artifacts
from there, the damage that it caused
and the fire that took place.
And so we have artifacts from California
that depict that tragedy there.
And then he, went and picked up
some items.
There was a gentleman
that was in the Spanish-American War,
and that came back from Fort to Franklin,
and he brought back artifacts from there.
And so he has them in the collection
here, the battleship Maine.
He has a piece of that
that he collected here.
And when they were going
to, tear down the USS Constitution,
he was right there
making sure that when they were homing
some of those artifacts
out to the museums,
he was there collecting
and grabbing something from there.
So he was a man of vision
and something that he knew
would have importance in American history,
and something that needed to be preserved
for future generations so we could see
those important artifacts. And
so he he's made an amazing contribution
that he doesn't even realize today.
When I said Lorenzo had
been sent here, he was sent here
and replaced President Thomas.
And President Thomas, had been overseeing
the community until 1863.
And then he went over to Bear Lake area.
And one of the big things
that Lorenzo was tasked with was,
getting helping, setting up a sawmill
and cutting lumber for the area.
And so Brigham
Young had purchased behind me
there's a stationary steam engine
and he purchased that
in Saint Louis and had that go up
the Missouri River to Fort Bend, Montana.
It was brought back here,
and it was set up in the canyon
to cut lumber for not some of the bigger
buildings in Salt Lake.
The tabernacle,
the old tabernacle was sitting there.
I cut the lumber for that,
and it cut some lumber for the season.
My, store and it sold sent the lumber
down there and was sold out of that store.
And then cut lumber here in the Valley.
And then it was sent over to Montpelier
to cut lumber for the railroad.
Was there a lumber?
And the railroad started progressing
into Idaho Territory and further up and
and so it was it was a huge contribution
because they had,
it helped us
build the areas up
with additional commerce.
Eventually the LDS church sold
that steam engine
to a private company, and they put it up
in the canyon here above.
Frank, Clint.
And he had cut lumber for quite some time.
And then is sat because,
for a while,
the gentleman that had that steam
engine, purchased it from the LDS church.
He had had two sons
that were working his sawmill,
and they had gone up there in the winter
time.
Eventually, they decided they needed
one more tree for, for an order.
And they went up there
and were kind of snow slide.
And both of them
were killed in the avalanche.
So the father devastated,
closed up the sawmill,
and he never used the steam engine again.
And Elliot
Butterworth, knowing about that story
and knowing the importance
of that artifact, there was a group,
a gentleman, that went up to the local
canyon, brought back the steam engine.
Now, this was of the later earlier models
that did not have
the wheels on the bottom.
It was a stationary steam engine,
so you had to have out loaded onto a wagon
and pulled by a number of mules
to move it.
Instead
of having the wheels attached to it.
So they went up and pulled it down here
and put it
not inside the building, but the building
was built over the top of it.
Announced the prized artifact
for the opening of the building in 1937.
So it has a long and important
history of contribution.
And we actually have a photograph here
in the museum that shows that steam
engine out, cutting lumber, this
this wood museum,
when individuals come in,
think it's a little cluttered,
but each artifact has an amazing story.
And that amazing story
tells the history of the state of Idaho
and those that build up the state here.
And it didn't start here.
They came across the United States
from other areas.
And so it's an amazing opportunity
to come in and see different
generations and their contribution
to the building of Idaho and
and what our state holds, how important
the people that came here
were to our progress.
And building up such a wonderful state
that we enjoy today.
And so I, I just
I just shudder
every time I think of some of the stories
I've learned
and the artifacts are used in the building
and progressing through the state
and bringing
so many blessings that we have here
today, it's just wonderful.
And I really encourage everyone to come
see some of these amazing things,
because there some of them are so unknown
and we just have
such a great opportunity
to go to museums and see unique artifacts
that can help, show us a different life
and a different time.
And I appreciate the contribution
that was given to those individuals
that build it, that the state.
And that's what
that's what we do in museums.
We look towards the future
to show future generations the importance
of contribution to our society
and our state and to America.
The Franklin Relic Home
Museum is very unique in that retrospect,
because Franklin did play a big part
in Yellowstone history.
Hard to believe, I know, but it does.
One of the unique things
we have here in the museum
is the
Yellowstone
National Park Transportation coach.
And that coach actually was used
within the park
and the,
the, the the way people travel to the park
on the through Idaho on the south.
And as they would travel
the old Yellowstone Highway
and then they would go up through Rexburg
and Idaho Falls and up through Ashton.
And so early on, I had shared the story,
with visitors that come in the
the wonder
how in the world we have this item.
As one of the gentlemen that lived here
in Franklin, he actually went up
to the park and drove coach
and the coaches were very popular
in the early on.
You just have the coach pick you up
and then take you into the park
for like a four day trip.
And each night you camp in the park and,
and then you go out.
And then when the railroad got there,
then you rode the railroad West
Yellowstone, and then they'd take you
through the park on the coaches.
So each coach was numbered,
and the Yellowstone
Transportation Company would do it.
Order from Abbott, Downing
and the particular coach
we have on the Yellowstone number is 29.
So once they received their orders,
they would number each coach
29 or off and on and on.
And so ours was used early on.
Ours was dated about 1903 to 1907,
when it was built.
And the gentleman
that drove coach up there,
he came home
with the invention of the automobile.
They banned coaches in the park
and all switched to the automobile.
And so they started
auctioning those coaches off,
and it went to a ranch
that was not too far from here.
And the gentleman
that drove Coach in his later
years knew that that ranch
was going to auction off the coach.
And so we ended up
getting that coach at the auction.
And that is one of the artifacts
that is here in the museum.
It's quite
unique because there's not a lot of
original coaches left that were used
in Yellowstone National Park.
There's maybe only 20 of them,
and there's it's
never had anything
any major work done on it.
Like a lot of them are,
working up there, with Rawhide Johnson
at the Cody Museum,
we were able to get some original,
order forms of the coach,
the numbering system that is on the body,
and he helped us
pinpoint those dates for our coach.
So that's kind of a proud artifact
we have that
we know that was used
in the first National Park of America.
And we treasure that item
because as today,
as we take our families through the park
and our cars and our comfort,
we look at the coaches
and people were just as excited
then to travel through the park
and see the wonder since we are today.
And so it's a great opportunity
to be able to show
individuals today what it
was like back then,
but still share the side of being able
to travel through the park
and see those wonders that we have.
The official mining
records are in the museum and,
you know, and the very first logging,
I sorry, the very first mining records
that I saw were showed territory
of Washington County of Spokane
and, about two months later,
the it changed to territory of Washington
County of Shoshone.
They form the own county
because of the number of people, men
that were coming into to mine.
And then, because of the distance
that, people in this area
had to go to the to,
courthouse to the county, county seat.
They, were trying to create a new,
a new, county.
And initially the Clearwater
County did not succeed in 1903,
but in 1904,
this area was annexed to Nez Perce County.
And then in 1911,
Clearwater County was formed.
Pierce initially was
had quite a large population,
and as the
Caucasian or white, miners left,
the Chinese took over.
And at one time,
the population here in Pierce was,
as far more Chinese than there were
white, white people.
And,
then that that kind of settled down.
But then, like John said in the,
the when the loggers came in, it, it
it's never been a huge town again.
It's never gotten as big as it was
when it was mining.
But it is,
right now it's about 500.
Headquarters was a booming town
at one time.
And because of the logging,
it was the major,
there were,
the railroad went into, headquarters and,
there were a
lot of logging logging trucks
that they did.
They had, the river camps
and the railroad camps
and then the logging, logging
trucks would move logs,
down to, the railroad or down to
of where a flume was available
to get the logs into the river.
But right now, headquarters,
there's very little in headquarters.
Now, when they shut down the logging,
it had to do with modernizing, supposedly,
they went from the railroad, moving the,
the, logs by rail
to moving them with trucks.
And so they, apparently
the line that comes from or if,
you know, up to headquarters,
the railroad line, there are, I believe,
42, trestles.
And so the maintenance of that, that,
track is very
it was very expensive to keep it going.
And apparently it was became cheaper
to load
the logs, on trucks and move in that way.
Okay.
They're very much the same as,
as any other area.
They're they're people
just trying to make a living and,
and, raise families. And,
so I'm
looking for the, their own niche in life.
And so it,
I think there's a special area,
I really like living here,
but for me, it's it's
my beginnings I lived in.
Or if, you know, I was raised in or if,
you know, my father was superintendent
State Hospital.
And so,
I wasn't really attached that much
to the logging industry, or to Pierce.
So I was more or,
or if, you know, with my center.
So, and state Hospital was I live
my father was required
to live on the state hospital grounds.
So we lived up there
and so my world was considerably different
than a loggers life.
So Bob Allen
worked for Potlatch for decades,
and he was interested in history.
And when a piece of,
equipment became obsolete,
he would ask permission to tuck it away
and save it for, for a museum.
And so for many years,
he collected a lot of old equipment. And,
in 1990, he actually opened the museum
and the, the first the cabin
that it's there is actually,
a cabin from,
Clearwater Timber Protective Association.
They had a, a headquarters
near headquarters, and,
they moved that cabin first,
and then they built the other smaller one.
And, storage the, shed,
to put things in.
And so he was, dedicated to
preserving the history of,
of the logging of the process.
And so.
Well, it was a great experience,
and we lived through the best of it.
However, when I started working
here, there was all virgin timber.
It was a where I was working,
we built a railroad over into Schofield
Creek.
There was no roads in there
and it was all big cedar, pine.
And so if you read for
headquarters, it was
the main,
potlatch office.
And, Howard
Bradbury was a superintendent
when I came here.
There was.
Oh, probably
4 to 500 men
working.
And sometimes
in the railroad camps
and in, river camps.
I retired because they shut down
the jeep mill.
the jeep mill
did. That caused a lot of.
Folks to quit working.
Not a lot.
Most of them were younger than me, and
I happened to be old enough
that it didn't bother me.
One time I was following about a two foot
white pine
and,
it was there was eight feet of snow
and I was down in the whole course.
We had a shovel or shovel of snow,
and I wasn't watching what I was doing.
And I had my shoulder up
against the tree,
and it was supposed to fall that way.
Well, I cut the corner off.
A tree kept pushing on my shoulder.
I looked up,
it was coming right over the top of me
so I couldn't get out of the hole.
So all I could do
is sit down with a stone.
That's what I did.
And that tree happened to be flat enough
that the snow held it up.
And it never touched me.
Another time
I was fallen a big white of fur.
And that was a real heavy tree.
And it wanted to go out that way.
I wanted to go that way.
And so I put my undercut in and started
just subtle little ways.
And that tree broke off.
There's that much wood. And,
I knew it was going to balance in the air.
Or when it hit the ground,
there was five foot of snow there.
And,
it, it did bounce in the air,
and I, I couldn't run,
and I just got on my hands and knees
and crawled as fast as I could.
And that tree hit right behind my feet
and pushed me down the hill
and covered me with snow.
We, sometime work six days a week,
year round.
Mud, snow, whatever.
There was a lot of them.
There were Swedes, Norwegians, Bohemians,
Danes, and probably ever country in Europe
and people working there.
They they came from mostly from Minnesota.
When the logging stopped there,
they came out here
most of those old fellows
didn't have a Social Security card.
So when they got to a certain age
where they
couldn't produce any more,
they had to retire.
There was nothing to retire on.
And Howard Bradbury would work with them
and get people in the old country
to verify their age and give them a card.
Oh, if he couldn't get them a card, no way
he would hire them in the summertime
to work on the building and headquarters.
And, they would wash
windows,
whatever needed to be done in town.
And that way they could buy their stuff
and a beer once in a while.
When they lived in Greer and the old folks
home, Mr.
Bradbury was a fine gentleman.
He probably no more men.
He was Karen Hughes.
He was a these people,
I know of that.
He was willing to talk
to anybody for a few minutes. Oh, I mean.
Time.
But he was a great man.
He took care of things in town.
Plus, he was over
all the railroad camps, the river camps,
and he had a foreman at each camp.
And between him and the foreman,
they decided
what they would do.
Well, we were hooked on to a a tree
length.
We'd cut it
as far as we could on both sides
with the bar we had,
and we hooked on to it
and pulled up stream
and it wouldn't break off.
And then we drifted down
and it pulled again.
It wouldn't break off.
And then I seen we was in trouble.
So I, I had an ax right by my hand
so I could cut the rope.
And I reached for the ax, and the water
hit me right in the chest,
and we went to the bottom
and crashed like an eggshell.
There was 4 or 5 of us in the boat, and,
I was one of them.
And I got in the current
and went down under the water.
When I come up,
I was in the middle of the river
and, I went down in the river
two and a half to three miles
and, finally the river spit me out.
I actually walked out of the river
when I got to out of the river,
I sat down on a stump
and I had a pocket watch.
I dumped the water out of it
and it said there was a difference
of 45 minutes
between when we went down and.
And I got the water out of it,
you know, coming down the river.
I had no control.
I went through some pretty heavy riffles.
I finally caught a little log,
and and that kind of broke the waves
as it went through them.
And,
I got down almost to salmon Crick
and, a cameraman was with us,
and he had three cameras
around in his neck, and they were winding
up, and he was trying to get them loose.
And I said, can you grab this log?
It was only six feet from me.
And he said, no, I can't do it.
And he went down and the river
spit him out there in an eddy.
And, he got out.
Used to.
We used cats and,
and hand saws and we,
when we got through skinning,
you could walk through the woods and
it was nice.
You could hunt there, you know,
now with this equipment there, you got now
it mashes everything down
and you can't walk through it.
Very few hand saws.
I knew the man
that surveyed the beaver flume
and,
He, said
when they got down there and finished it,
they put water in it and trailer
the logger to.
And they went clear across the river.
So they had to change
the slope of the flume right
where they put it in there.
This this courthouse was built in 1863.
They were mining was just going.
How could they make millions of dollars
being taken out of here?
And they ended up with a lot of robberies
taking place
as they were taking the gold from here
down to Lewiston.
So they decided
they need some county government.
So they organized, the county here.
And this was the first county courthouse
in Idaho.
It was built in 63, in fact,
you see, the bars up there in that window.
That's where the jail was.
And they put kegs of nails
and put them into the in the wall
so the prisoners couldn't cut their way
out of this log, the long jail.
And then the second floor
was where the county commissioners met.
And that was the big government,
this county, this was still Washington
Territory during that time.
It was Shoshone County,
which was all basically all of North Idaho
except for later
County and Nez Perce County.
So it was a huge, huge county,
and all of governing was done from here.
And this was put out to bid.
I forget the amount of money
they awarded for to build this courthouse,
but it was the first courthouse in Idaho
and the first governing body in Idaho
as it is basically the territory of Idaho.
Sure, they would take the gold from here
by mule down to Lewiston,
and it was an arduous trip.
They had to go down to the Clearwater.
They had a ferry there across Clearwater.
Then they go up across the prairie.
It passed where Nez Perce is now and down
through a cul de sac into Lewiston.
So it was a it was a long, arduous trip,
and they had to take all the banks
where these crooks would hang out
and they'd rob these people, these
mule skinners
who were taking the gold down
to down to Lewiston.
And they decided
they needed some government
and that's when they established
the county here, Shoshone County and that.
And then they got got the sheriff
and they got some passes.
And then when they started governing
and they did it basically
to stop the violence, they had one fella
who stopped taking gold
because he was a feared for his life.
And one of those gangs came back
and shot up an owner of a bar, because he
talked back to him
when I was riding back from Lewiston.
It was a wild, violent place.
And that was the genesis
for starting a county government here.
So they get some law
and order, more order than law.
Probably
major
gold rush before this was in California.
They all came from the East.
This was the first major gold rush
where they all came from the West.
They came from this,
the west coast, from the logging
camps up in the Olympic Peninsula,
mostly from Portland.
Portland was the funnel at that time.
It was the it was the major
metropolitan area at that time in Seattle.
There was just a sawmill.
There was no basically said here at all.
And so it was Portland.
And then Pierce became
basically the second largest city
in Washington Territory after Portland.
I forget how many thousand,
but it was thousands of people here.
And then they the work was incredibly hard
because they had to get water
funneled in to get to
the sluice boxes
to get the overload off of the gold.
And it was, for instance,
what guy who would walk three miles up
it, have to dam up the creek
to get ahead of water,
to come down to flush through the
the sluice boxes.
He get up in the morning,
go up and release the dam
so the water would come down
to flush through and he walked back.
At night.
We all wet, all running, all day.
Walk another three miles up to put a
dam on the creek
again so they get another head of water
for the next day and walk back,
all in a day's work.
So he's walked
12 miles plus worked all day
to get the gold off out of the six boxes.
That's how tough those guys were.
But the single greatest guy
in my in my experience
and is he has a huge tombstone
right here in the Pierce Cemetery
was was
it it was his name was Israel Cohen,
and he was a county commissioner.
He was in the territorial legislature,
but he also
then became the first postman
and post carrier.
And he would carry the mail from here
down to the Clearwater,
across up again to the great,
across the prairie and down to Lewiston,
all on his back, 30, 40 pounds of mail.
And in the weather he did it on snowshoes,
and he had a club foot.
How's that for tough?
And when the mining disappeared,
the logging came in.
They started here in 26,
and this was one of the finest low
elevation pine
forests in the United States.
I forget how many millions and billions of
actually board feet if they measured it.
They estimated there was here
and they came in basically
with it built, in fact,
that they got a generator.
They took up to the head of Beaver Creek,
and in one year they built flumes.
Flumes or what?
Or funnels that they used to take the logs
down to the river for the log drive.
They saw it and built about.
I think it was 8 or 12 miles of film.
One summer, and they would take the lumber
down the flume
with water to get it down
to the next section of the flume.
It was just incredible, incredible work
those carpenters built,
and you'd have to see pictures of the film
to understand
what an undertaking that was.
Yeah, crossbars
that they, they were built on.
And you had the flume
itself was a funnel to get the logs down,
and then you had to be very careful
about the amount of.
They had sidewalks along the flume.
They had flume walkers,
they had crank telephones.
And they had those dams
where you let water into the flume
to get the water to float the logs down.
But you had to be really careful,
because if you put too much water
and you got swift the log
to jump the flume,
if you had too little water,
they jam up and
and call the transport of logs down.
And so those flume walkers would call up
and they know
when to release water,
how much water to release.
So they would give just exactly
the right amount of water
to get those logs down to the down,
down to the river for their log drive.
It was incredible feat.
I forget how many miles of flume
ended up building
before they stopped the log drives,
but they would have these holding ponds
where they'd have that
thousand thousands of board feet of logs
and they'd roll them in with PVC center.
The end of the
flume in the water was going
and I have pictures of the lost and mill.
The pond was just filled with logs
after the log drive.
It was just an incredible undertaking
and what they couldn't get,
of course they had to have
had to be on the slope down to the river
to have the flumes inland.
They used the trains and the what?
The river camps were letters camp T camp,
actually camp H, campy
and the railroad camps were numbers.
Camp 14, camp 16. Hold it.
And what they couldn't
take out down through the river,
they would had built a railroad
from here down to Lewiston
and they take them out by train camps.
Prairie came up the Lewiston,
and then Potlatch
built its own railroads out to the camps,
and they had miles.
I forget how many miles of railroad
that they built
to to bring the logs in from the camps
where they couldn't get them down to the
logs, down to the river.
Well, what happened was that
they brought in
an infusion of people into Idaho.
I mean, you had thousands of people here.
Yeah, the population
and then when they discovered
silver up and in the court lanes,
and they moved the county seat
from Shoshone County to Pierce to Mullen,
which later went to Wallace,
and then the mining brought
people in.
And they also had another gold rush down
and out, out of Granville.
And that was what the first
draw of population
in, so people could see what was here.
And then once they came in here
and saw all the timber,
then they said, wow,
this is there's more than just gold here.
Here's, here's a
incredibly rich, diverse
forest unparalleled
anywhere else in the United States
for a low elevation forest.
And so that brought people in.
And as Galen was saying,
there are 4 or 500 people in headquarters
at the height of the logging.
They started with horses, crosscut saws.
My dad used to say that in a horse camp
there were three key people.
If you didn't have those three people,
you're not going to have
a good logging camp.
And that was the camp cook
who fed the lumberjacks, the barn boss
and fed the horses, and the five
who kept the crosscut style sharp.
And each sawyer
pair of
sawyers would have their own saw,
and they take them in.
And the salt shop is right down there
at the museum.
And they file the filers would file
the saws, they'd leave them for one day.
They come back and get a new set of file
sizes.
The next day,
I remember going into a filing shop
and there was iron filings
all over the floor.
That's that's how they kept to the horse
logging camps going.
It started in Potlatch.
Bill dairy was brought out
by Weyerhaeuser, built a railroad
from Potlatch over to Bovill
that walked into the Milwaukee Road
and they had access to the markets.
And then when they came down here,
the lowest and they had the railroad out,
but for the for the lumber to get out,
and it was just a sawmill then.
No pulp mill.
Pulp mill came in in 1951, long
after that.
The logging started for the sawmill.
And so they took it all out by train
from lowest into the market.
It's a matter of fact.
They came in later there.
They had the Chinese Exclusion Act,
as you probably know,
that they weren't supposed to be here.
And they came in
and they would go where they.
But when the miners left here
and went to the next rush, which was,
I forget, the name of the gold rush,
the next gold rush, but,
they would come in and have the pilings
and they would go through
what would been left.
A lot of these miners would high grade.
They get the easy gold.
The Chinese had come
and get this difficult stuff,
but they're really taken advantage of.
They if they found some gold, some of the
Caucasian come in and jump their claims
and they had no recourse really,
they were terribly taken advantage of.
They had a temple here in Pierce
where they worshiped.
And in fact, that that,
The the
altar and the some of the paraphernalia
for that temple are in the museum.
And Rufino
and so they had
and they had the big burner here
where they quick ahead of the
one of the major stars was murdered.
And what had happened is two Chinese,
had come in from, Portland
and they found out that the white,
the Caucasian guy was getting all of
the business from the Chinese miners.
So they had him killed, and I
they finally found the ledger from
that guy's store about ten years ago.
And I was able to discover
for the first time the reason that came in
the Caucasian was getting
all this business from the Chinese miners.
And the tongs didn't like that
they had what they called Chinese tongs,
which were organizations formed
like sort of like fraternal groups.
And,
they were taking them up to Mulund
for a trial.
And about six miles out of here,
a posse stopped him and the hanged him.
They have a sign out here at the pro
going to peers from peers out there.
We I or they say the hanging tree.
That's not correct.
It was the old road was down
by the creek there
path had a Chinese cemetery.
My grandmother always said
that they had it in the wrong place,
that it was down
further down on the old Peirce Road,
not the current Peirce Road,
but they hanged them.
Right.
Right there on the spot.
That's that was long.
The Wild West
had come in to kill the store
manager of the store,
because he was getting all the business
from the Chinese miners
instead of the Chinese store.
The tongs wanted the money.
They were organized.
They wanted the money from the money
that was coming into the stores
here in Pearce.
And that money was drying up.
So they came up to see what
the problem was.
They found out that the I can't think
of the fella's name who had this store.
I've read it somewhere here.
What's that? Fraser. Fraser.
Yeah.
But so they. Were being taken.
And he was getting all the business
and they wanted to stop that, get
the money flowing again
to Portland from the tongs.
So they murdered him
and they, then they
the posse came and got the people
that they thought had murdered him.
The two Chinese or three,
I think there were six, maybe
5 or 5 Chinese.
And they taken them on their way up
to Shoshone, up in Mullan,
which was now the
the county seat for trial.
And six miles out of here, they stuck
posse stopped them and hanged them all.
Yes, they probably were guilty.
The that's the irony,
but that's not
how it's supposed to happen.
You're supposed to have a hearing
before you have.
You say in the army,
you know what you have.
Ready. Aim! Fire!
You have ready! Fire! Aim!
And they were ready. Fire! Aim!
Actually, governor McConnell
was he had gone back to the
an expo in Chicago and
and talked about all this great Timberland
because he'd just become a state
and the just having become a state,
they didn't have any source of income
very slight population,
a small population.
And they needed
they needed the money to govern.
And they the state, every time
the territory became a state,
they got to select
a certain amount of land, a state, land.
And the, territorial governor
got to make that selection.
Of course,
they selected a lot of the timber land
because that's
where they considered the wealth to be.
And so a lot of that was in
what is now later County
was then later County to actually and
what they
did was they put it up for bid
so they could get some money
and warehouse or came in and started
the mill at Potlatch.
That was called
the Potlatch Lumber Company here
and in Clearwater County,
it was the Clearwater Timber Company,
but they were both owned by Weyerhaeuser,
where I said, come out.
And when you saw the
you actually made a trip out
and, saw the timber
and they fact they signed the
and you gave the capital further
the took $500,000, which would now be,
I think like 6 million,
something like that
in today's money.
And to get Clearwater
timber established and that's
when they started the logging and,
but they waited
until they found the logging and they
the potlatch mill was,
was, still operating.
Then they started, a mill in Elk River
because they'd had a,
they'd had a blowdown.
John, where I discovered a blow down of
six, about 6 million board feet of timber.
So they build a mill.
And in Elk River to log that timber.
They did it,
but they found out they had a problem.
The snow was so deep.
They've had trouble getting the
the lumber out of the yards
and the lumber onto the trains
to get it up to up to Saint Mary's,
where they could hook up with
the with the Milwaukee Road.
And so John Warehouses said, look,
we have all this snow,
we have this river to Lewiston.
You know what could be better?
What easier way to get timber down.
We don't have any snow in Lewiston.
So that's
when they actually burned down the mill.
And and,
Elk River and built the mill and,
in Lewiston
that I think it was completed in
like 27, 28
Potlatch.
They started logging here in 26,
but I'm not sure just
when the mill was completed there,
but they dammed up their Clearwater and
had a lot big log pond there for the mill.
Gotcha.
Later County was they were smart.
They needed they needed the votes
from later County to create a state.
And they said they wouldn't do it
unless we got the university.
They first planned to have the university
at Eagle Rock.
You know, our Eagle Rock is Idaho Falls.
Exactly.
And they said, we will not vote to become
a state unless we get the university.
And that's when it went from Eagle
Rock up to Moscow.
And then they went there,
but they would vote until they built
the first administration building,
because they wanted to make damn sure
that not only were they promising it,
but it was going to happen.
So they built the first administration
building just a year before.
Later, our county voted to become a state.
And that's how how late
our county got the university.
It was
blackmail, actually, in today's terms.
Well, I think one of the most colorful.
Characters was George McKinnon,
who was an all country Scotsman,
and he was a camp
foreman, worked for my dad out of camp 14,
and he was a curmudgeonly guy.
And, and, during the war,
they had trouble getting lumberjacks
because all the men were young
men were in the in the service.
And so they're getting something.
But you have to know
is the old country lumberjacks,
the Finland's, the Swedes, the Norwegians,
the Bohemians all wore suspenders
and they all chewed snow.
You never saw a cigaret.
You never saw a belt.
And they crop off the bottom of their
their pants so they would get caught up
in the in the limbs, in the woods.
Well, they're bringing these cowboys in.
And of course, during the war,
all manufactured
cigarets are going to the troops.
So you had
you had a bag of, of tobacco
and you had these little folders of, of,
cigaret paper.
And you have to roll your own and judgment
and then you're either
sending these cowboys out the log.
And George McKinnon called up my dad
and he said, Howard,
I don't want any more of these
goddamn cowboys.
He said, I can't get any work out of them.
They aren't rolling a cigaret.
They're pulling up their pants.
And and then one time,
my dad thought he was doing them a favor
to send out some watermelons.
They that you get some fresh fruit because
most of the fruit came out of tin cans.
And in the camps.
He called up there and he said, Howard,
no more watermelons,
said,
they're 90% water and 10% disappointment.
So that was one of the colorful characters
that that I'm aware of,
that my dad used to talk about
each followed their own,
their own trade, like the Sawyers,
tended to be sweet and the,
the Teamsters tended to be Norwegians.
They not wasn't a rule or anything, but
that's just how they sort of gravitated.
It further came wherever the logging was.
Good.
And they and then they had the bunkhouses
where they'd stay.
They had those old angle
iron cot beds with mattresses.
That was after they'd had a strike at 36
before 1936.
They, the lumberjacks, were served
food on tin cups and tinplate.
There were no showers.
They had to find their own water
to shower.
My dad said the bedbugs were so bad.
Sometimes you have to go out
in out of the bunkhouse to sleep
just to get away from the bedbugs.
And these lumberjacks
go from camp to camp with their packs, ax.
And if they had to have their own bedroll,
and then they had to go down
to the horse barn to get straw,
to put on the flat surface for a bed,
and they finally had a strike.
In fact, my mother had to go through
the picket line at the Pierce divide
to get to the hospital to have me and.
But after that they had ceramic dinner
where they had every,
every bunkhouse was fumigated for bedbugs,
they had showers and they had toilets.
So it was a it was a huge difference.
And then the pay almost doubled
and it went from 12 hours.
I forget it was usually 12 hours,
six days a week.
And I'm not sure just
when it went to eight hours.
And I mean in the 30s, I think
with the fair labor relations there.
And that was.
The the IWW that was organizing.
The IWW.
Yeah,
yeah.
The Wobblies
was not just the Lumberjacks
went on strike that year.
The longshoreman on the coast,
the seaman all went on strike.
It was a major, major strike.
And that's when they called the governor,
called out the National Guard
and quelled the strike
coming.
The miners were from all over.
In fact, in Pierce,
during the mining days,
there were a lot of Southerners because.
The Civil War was going on,
and a lot of Missouri,
I think, was a free state.
And a lot of the people
in some of these border states
didn't want to fight for the Union.
So they came west to escape conscription
into the
into the Union army.
And then they got in a lot of fights here
with the with the people
that were supporting the union.
It was a very divided
mining camp here,
and a lot of struggles between the,
the Confederate, those
who were sympathetic to the Confederacy
and those who were Union rights.
Basically,
the only people populating north
central Idaho at that time
was the Nez Perce tribe.
And up in Walla Walla,
you had the Cayuse tribe,
and you had the Palouse tribe and that.
But basically it was all Native Americans,
and they put the gold discoveries
dead as they brought in the
miners, which were
people that were
and basically it was very unpopular
because they
they created the reservations in 19 1840.
And then they were the whites
were coming in to the reservations.
And we're not supposed to be here.
So it was a it was a very, very tense
time with the native tribes they created.
Headquarters was company owned town.
Pierce had a lot of it basically depended
on the logging industry.
We IPE, on the other
hand, was more farming and ranching.
It is the economy in this part of Idaho.
If it weren't for the logging industry,
there would be no economy at all.
Clearwater County large.
Yeah.
In Lake County
you have quite a bit of timber land,
but it's basically agricultural,
as is Louis County, but.
And Nez Perce County,
but Clearwater County, where we are today,
there is no economy other than logging.
The only thing besides that
Naafi, though, is the penitentiary
in the State Hospital North.
Those are the other two major employers,
except for that.
So logging,
one of the things you find with loggers,
they're they're very hardworking,
very decent,
but very independent people.
They tend to have a master
of their own drums.
God bless them for doing it.
There's no herd mentality
in the logging industry.
Everybody knows who they are and what they
want to be and what they're going to do.
And it's a it's a joy
to be around the loggers.
It's gone from horses to used to have.
You'd have a horse,
you have a teamster with a horse,
you'd have two sawyers, 12
to crosscut saw, you'd have a person
who would dig down a scale
and start talking in a wetter down
to get to the low down on the
as low as you can on a track.
You don't want to waste that word.
You wanted a low, low stomp, and you had,
the people that were
at the landings
where they'd log all the logs into
where they could either be into the flumes
to take them down to the river
or onto a loading ramp
to be fully loaded onto the railroad cars.
Now they have one machine that cuts
the log, cuts the tree, custom
cuts limbs off, cut them in the logs
and logs them so they that one
machine is replaced, probably 6 or 7
loggers that would have been involved
in that process
before that mechanize, mechanization
of the logging took place.
They, they
in this area, they've clearcut everything
in their plantings, some of it back.
But basically we've gone from a forest
to basically
an agricultural situation
to just growing trees as a crop.
So the idea of a forest is a forest
that supports wildlife, birds.
It's gone.
It's it's out the window.
And it's tragic because if it keeps up,
there's going to be no economy
in Clearwater County.
There'll be no logs left.
And these these families
that depend on logging industry to
to survive
are going to be without any work.
And it's going to be a disaster
not only economically for the people,
but it's a disaster ecologically.
Nope.
No trees, no canopy to filter
the sunlight going into the snow.
So we have a fast runoff. You get floods.
There are no trees for the burst to nest
in, no trees for the beavers
to create dams
with no cover for the animals.
It's it's an ecological disaster.
And you can quote me on that.
But file T Farnsworth was born and, in
Utah and Beaver County.
And if you go to Beaver County,
there is his grandfather was a facility.
Farnsworth.
So the they were very early pioneers
and he was very active
in the county history of an area.
So his family moved up here
and they ran a farm east of here
and was the Clark area.
Very brilliant young man.
And when he was,
plowing, their field,
he got this idea about.
And so we went,
to school the next day
and talked to his chemistry teacher, Mr.
Tolan.
And on the blackboard he went through
and drew things and gave him his idea.
So that's
where the Rigby connection comes in there.
He did not.
He only he did not graduate
from the high school here.
He left probably a year or so after that
and was able to get funding.
And with a lab in San Francisco.
But when it came time
for,
To get the patent,
you know, the laws of patents,
you have to be able to prove that
your concept first one, you developed.
So they ask him, now what?
Who can we get?
So he had been back to this area,
for all that time.
But he said my chemistry teacher.
And so they contact this
chemistry teacher
who was still teaching here,
and this was in the 30s.
He went and, he went to the patent
hearing and had that patent here.
And he was able to go through
and on the board.
Sure.
Exactly what, file I had told him.
And so that's the grounds
that it got for the museum.
I mean, excuse me,
that he got for the patent,
but, years later,
in the 1950s,
he wanted to, to recognize
the role that the community played.
So he came to Rigby and,
spoke in the, LDS Tabernacle here
and presented some of the original tubes
to the high school.
And so I went to this high school,
and in the library
there was this glass case,
and in there there were,
those tubes.
And so that's where the, Ruby contact,
connection to file a T Farnsworth.
You know, he's one of those.
He was a brilliant man,
but he was not a very good businessman.
And like so many other brilliant man,
they're not necessarily good businessmen.
So he never made much money off
any of his inventions.
I mean, he made over a thousand of them.
So some of his materials
are in the Inventors Hall of Fame
and so on.
So this is something that the community
wanted to do was to have something.
And so for years and years
and years, they raised fun and and so on.
And, this is where it grew out of.
And we knew we didn't have enough
just to do fill out in here.
So it was a, healing history.
So that's when the two groups,
joined together.
His wife, Pam, lived in Salt Lake City.
And some of these items that we have,
I was a courier,
so I would go and pick up something
to bring back to the museum,
because she lived on Garfield Street,
which is on the SugarHouse area.
So I have been to her home
a number of times.
And then her book, This Vision,
which is a personal account
of because she was not only a wife,
she was a partner.
So she was with them
at every step of his inventions.
So it's a very personal account,
unfortunately, and a much better editor,
because there's a lot of little things
that she made mistakes, that
if you had a good editor that was a cart
like Pearl Harbor Day is December
7th, that December 8th.
Sure. But it is.
She tells a lot of stories that you're
not going to find in other sources.
So she visited,
I think at least once here
she was in the, town parade.
And, and then mom and I had met her,
a number of times, so very nice lady.
She had a,
a basement full of whatever.
I mean, there is so many books
because, you know,
you know, professional people, they have
he has,
all these bound volumes of magazines,
chemistry magazines
and different science magazines and said.
So I went through a lot of things
and,
picking at what my, the
time I, she wanted, so
but she was very nice.
I'd met her, as I said, a number of times,
and I would when they ran out of books
of decent vision, I'd go and pick up a box
because, they privately publish it.
They could, you know, I don't know if if,
a publisher wouldn't take it or whatever,
but since his death, of course, I've had,
at least six books written on him,
and, a lot of publishers doing it
with the way that the patterns for them,
they were for a very short period of time.
Then World War Two came
and and for us was a horrible business.
And, and so RCA had the money
and, he sold a lot of his patterns for,
for below of what
they should have been sold for.
I think that it's important
to find out where we've come from,
because I think if you don't know
where you've come from, it's
really hard to know where you're going.
And certain things
that we've done in the past.
These are items that you can say, see,
this is what we came, this is what we did,
and this is how the improvements
that we made.
And, you know,
we've got here all these sewing machine,
I mean, the washing machines here.
And you can see the for project.
Yeah.
Progress going through and how they went
from one
to the other and development in it.
So I think that's a way to really
to show young people and that they can
what they can do
and make an impact for what
you're doing today and find a new way
to grow it in the future.
And also, it's a way sometimes it's
finding ways of making things better.
This is a problem.
How do we find a solution for it?
And a lot of that goes
not only in having an idea
it's going through and seeing
what other people have tried in the past.
And, because
it's not very often that you have someone
that comes with a totally, completely
original idea that no one's ever
thought of any way whatsoever.
What the way that there may be
a portion of the story.
And that's a way with television
that, you know,
what he did
was something that was unique,
but he'd built upon
what was done in the past.
Farnsworth was not born here
in Rigby, Idaho.
He was born in Indian Creek, Utah,
which is down near Beaver, Utah.
His family was farmers down there.
Farm ground down in that part of Utah
is not the best.
And, his family moved up here
for a brief period of time
to try and better themselves.
Rogers was only actually here
about three years,
and some time it was actually spent here.
It's ended there.
High school here in, in,
Rigby.
And, and and in 1922,
when he was going to school here way,
he was.
As I was looking at some,
History that we had in, on the computer,
it was written by his wife
as he was listing the field,
he got the idea of how he could
produce pictures electronically.
Well,
they say that he was a recording engineer.
His wife was asking if he looked back
and saw the various,
rows created by the disc in the field.
He thought he could produce pictures
like, chronically,
because we've been doing some studying
about electrons and stuff
and do it
one line at a time, very rapidly,
which is exactly how pictures
were originally made for television.
Well, he,
was talking with his, high school
teacher, explaining
how he thought he could produce pictures,
electronically, basically television.
And there's,
he made a drawing on the chalkboard
for his teacher explaining basically,
the camera to would work
and, as he was explaining that teachers
thought the idea could possibly work,
he thought enough about it.
Wonder what
he made this drawing on the chalkboard
in the high school for his teacher.
And, he, he left the classroom.
His teacher made a copy of that drawing.
They kept it.
And that became very important
for Farnsworth later on,
Farnsworth applied for a patent
for that particular process.
He did receive the patent RCA
with electronic giant of the day.
And,
they disputed his that they don't know.
We came up with the idea first.
Exactly what went to court on that?
His teacher found out what was going on
and actually went back and testified
before the patent committee
as to the exact date
the Farnsworth came up with the idea.
So Farnsworth
was able to keep that pattern.
It ended up costing RCA $1 million
for the use of that particular process.
He did create his own company.
He, entered the market
about the worst thing
he could possibly enter the market
with during the depression.
The first TV that
he produced actually was not produced here
in Rigby, Idaho,
which trying to be
the birthplace of television
because he came up with the idea
while he was here,
the first TV he produced
was not produced, ran.
It was produced in San Francisco,
California,
where he received some financial backing.
There not necessarily exact tubes
that he would use.
The tubes that Farnsworth did present
for the high school.
The first original tubes
are no longer here in Rigby.
They were in our
in our Rigby High School.
They were started in the library,
in a special case in the in the library.
Rigby high school library,
years ago, there were some Vander
there was some vandalism
took place in the high school.
They did not touch the tubes.
The principal was very concerned
that that something might happen to him.
So he basically gave our tubes away.
They ended up in BYU. Provo.
His family moved back to the Provo,
Utah area
from here, catch it right where it did
not graduate from high school here.
He actually graduated high school
in Provo, Utah.
He did attend Brigham
Young University of Provo.
He had to drop out to help
to support his family financially.
Before he received his degree,
which was basically set up to,
display how
various communities around the area
would have looked, a number of years ago,
agricultural, when one area was,
Megan schools
like, of course, the Rigby areas.
Was the Rigby area.
There's so many things in here that,
I, Enjoy.
I used a lot of the things
that were in here.
I'm not a young person by any means.
Most have seen that,
we cleaned the sign outside of.
Rigby. Claims us to be
the birthplace of television.
So I enjoyed telling him why
we make that claim.
A lot of, the misconception
that Farnsworth was born here.
That is not the case.
They have a misconception
that the first TV he produced
was actually made here.
There again, that is not the case.
So it brings up the chance
to bring up some to clear up
some misconceptions
that people have certainly.
Well, most of us watch TV and it wouldn't
be here if it wasn't provided truth.
The snow
plain, that's what they're called.
They were, never commercially produced.
The snow plane is does not fly.
It actually goes across the snow.
They work much like a swamp boat.
The propellers and the back of them.
And, as I said,
they were never commercially produced.
Years ago, there was, in Roberts, Idaho.
They did a,
a chart of all
usually around the 1st of January,
and they would do various races and stuff.
And then those things were actually raced
during that carnival, along
with chariot races and all kinds of stuff
that went on during that.
This whole museum is basically things that
were used many years ago.
A lot of people
have we take them through here.
We take, school groups are usually in the
in the spring, we do what we call
a treasure hunt, which gives them items
to look for in these particular rooms.
And, one of the things
that I have to encourage you about is,
one of the things we have to look for
is a hay knife.
Now, most people don't
know what a hay knife is.
A hay knife was
used when the hay was not baled,
hay was cut and put in a loose stack.
The hay knife, if I had one, was
would be, I could show you.
But they had two handles on
and they were used to cut a section
of hay out of that stack.
So, so that you could actually read
a section of the livestock.
Otherwise it would mat down
and be very hard to get out of the stack.
And there's just
basically a myriad of things
that in many cases are not reused anymore.
Couple of things that I
never thought would become obsolete
in my lifetime
that I've used extensively.
And one of them is a film camera.
A film camera
basically is not used anymore,
and also a typewriter.
If you don't know what things are,
how are you going to improve on on things
like these things, you know, about?
Because they weren't happy
with the way things were.
So they made them better.